Phyllis Rodriguez: We are here today
فيليس: نحن هنا اليوم
because of the fact
بسبب حقيقة
that we have what most people consider
ان لدينا ما يعتبره اغلب الناس
an unusual friendship.
صداقة غريبة
And it is.
و هي كذلك.
And yet, it feels natural to us now.
و مع ذلك ,نشعر انها طبيعية بالنسبة لنا الان
I first learned
لقد عرفت
that my son had been in the World Trade Center
ان ابني كان في مركز التجارة العالمي
on the morning of September 11th, 2001.
في صباح الحادي عشر من سبتمبر 2001
We didn't know
لم نعرف
if he had perished yet
اذا كان قد توفى
until 36 hours later.
إلا بعد 36 ساعة
At the time,
في ذلك الوقت
we knew that it was political.
عرفنا انه كان حدثا سياسيا
We were afraid of what our country was going to do
لقد كنا خائفين مما كانت ستفعله بلادنا
in the name of our son --
باسم ابننا
my husband, Orlando, and I and our family.
انا و زوجي اورلاندو وعائلتنا
And when I saw it --
و عندما رأيته
and yet, through the shock,
و بالرغم من الصدمة
the terrible shock,
الصدمة المريعة
and the terrible explosion in our lives, literally,
و الانفجار المريع في حياتنا ,حرفيا
we were not vengeful.
لم نكن انتقاميين
And a couple of weeks later
و بعد عدة اسابيع
when Zacarias Moussaoui was indicted
عندما اتهم زكريا موسوي
on six counts of conspiracy to commit terrorism,
في ست تهم تتعلق بالتآمر لارتكاب أعمال إرهابية ،
and the U.S. government called for a death penalty
و طالبت حكومة الولايات المتحدة بعقوبة الاعدام
for him, if convicted,
اذا تمت ادانته
my husband and I spoke out
انا و زوجي تكلمنا
in opposition to that, publicly.
ضد ذلك ,علنا
Through that
خلال ذلك
and through human rights groups,
و عبر مجموعات حقوق الانسان
we were brought together
اجتمعنا مع كثير
with several other victims' families.
من اهالي ضحايا اخرين
When I saw Aicha in the media,
عندما رأيت عائشة في وسائل الاعلام
coming over when her son was indicted,
خروجها عندما تم اتهام ابنها
and I thought, "What a brave woman.
و فكرت"يا لها من امرأة شجاعة
Someday I want to meet that woman when I'm stronger."
يوم ما اريد ان التقي تلك المرأة عندما اكون اقوى"
I was still in deep grief;
كنت ما ازال في حزن عميق
I knew I didn't have the strength.
كنت اعلم انني لا املك القوة
I knew I would find her someday,
علمت انني سأجدها يوما ما
or we would find each other.
او سنجد بعضنا
Because, when people heard that my son was a victim,
لانه عندما سمع الناس ان ابني كان ضحية
I got immediate sympathy.
تلقيت تعاطف فوري
But when people learned
لكن عندما علم الناس
what her son was accused of,
ما اتهم به ابنها
she didn't get that sympathy.
لم تتلق ذلك التعاطف
But her suffering is equal to mine.
لكن معاناتها مساوية لمعاناتي
So we met in November 2002,
وهكذا التقينا في نوفمبر 2002
and Aicha will now tell you
و عائشة ستخبركم الان
how that came about.
كيف كان ذلك
(Translator) Aicha el-Wafi: Good afternoon, ladies and gentlemen.
(المترجم) عائشة: طبتم مساء سيداتي سادتي
I am the mother of Zacarias Moussaoui.
انا ام زكريا موسوي
And I asked
و سألت
the Organization of Human Rights
منظمة حقوق الانسان
to put me in touch with the parents of the victims.
ان يصلوني بأباء الضحايا
So they introduced me
و هكذا عرفوني
to five families.
بخمس عائلات
And I saw Phyllis, and I watched her.
و رأيت فيليس و شاهدتها
She was the only mother in the group.
كانت الام الوحيدة في المجموعة
The others were brothers, sisters.
البقية كانو اخوة ,اخوات
And I saw in her eyes
ورأيت في عينيها
that she was a mother, just like me.
انها كانت ام مثلي تماما
I suffered a lot as a mother.
عانيت الكثير كأم
I was married when I was 14.
زوّجت عندما كنت في ال14
I lost a child when I was 15,
خسرت طفل عندما كنت في ال15
a second child when I was 16.
و طفل اخر في ال16
So the story with Zacarias was too much really.
وهكذا القصة مع زكريا كانت كثيرة جدا حقا
And I still suffer,
و مازلت اعاني
because my son
بسبب ابني
is like he's buried alive.
كأنه دفن حيا
I know she really cried for her son.
انا اعرف انها بكت حقا لاجل ابنها
But she knows where he is.
لكنها تعلم اين هو
My son, I don't know where he is.
ابني ,لا اعلم اين هو
I don't know if he's alive. I don't know if he's tortured.
لا اعلم اذا كان حيا ,لا اعلم اذا كان يعذب
I don't know what happened to him.
لا اعلم ما حدث له
So that's why I decided to tell my story,
لهذا قررت حكاية قصتي
so that my suffering is something positive for other women.
كي تكون معاناتي شيئا ايجابيا لنساء اخريات
For all the women, all the mothers that give life,
لكل النساء, كل الامهات اللاتي اعطين الحياة
you can give back,
يمكنكن ان تعطين مرة اخرى
you can change.
يمكنكن التغيير
It's up to us women,
انه راجع الينا نحن النساء
because we are women,
لاننا نساء
because we love our children.
لاننا نحب اطفالنا
We must be hand-in-hand
يجب ان نكون يدا بيد
and do something together.
و نفعل شيئا معا
It's not against women,
انه ليس ضد النساء
it's for us, for us women,
انه لنا ,لنا النساء
for our children.
لاطفالنا
I talk against violence, against terrorism.
انا اتكلم ضد العنف ,ضد الارهاب
I go to schools
انا اذهب الى المدارس
to talk to young, Muslim girls
لاتكلم مع الفتيات المسلمات الصغيرات
so they don't accept to be married against their will very young.
حتى لا يقبلو بأن يزوّجو ضد رغبتهم في سن صغيرة
So if I can save one of the young girls,
و اذا استطعت ان انقذ واحدة من الفتيات اليافعات
and avoid that they get married and suffer as much as I did,
و تجنب ان يزوّجو و يعانو بقدر ما عانيت
well this is something good.
اذن هذا شيء جيد
This is why I'm here in front of you.
ولهذا السبب أنا هنا أمامكم.
PR: I would like to say
فيليس : انا اريد ان اقول
that I have learned so much from Aicha,
اني تعلمت الكثير من عائشة
starting with that day we had our very first meeting
بداية من اليوم الذي اجتمعنا فيه لاول مرة
with other family members --
مع افراد عائلاتنا
which was a very private meeting with security,
الذي كان اجتماع خاص للغاية مع حماية
because it was November 2002,
لانه كان في نوفمبر 2002
and, frankly, we were afraid of the super-patriotism of that time in the country --
و بصراحة كنا خائفين من الوطنية الزائدة في ذلك الوقت في البلاد
those of us family members.
اولئك منا افراد العائلات
But we were all so nervous.
لكن كلنا كنا متوترين للغاية
"Why does she want to meet us?"
"لماذا تريد ان تقابلنا ؟"
And then she was nervous.
و بعد ذلك كانت هي متوترة
"Why did we want to meet her?"
"لماذا اردنا ان نقابلها؟"
What did we want from each other?
ماذا اردنا من بعضنا؟
Before we knew each others' names, or anything,
قبل ان نعرف اسماء بعضنا او اي شيء
we had embraced and wept.
قد تعانقنا وبكىنا.
Then we sat in a circle
ثم جلسنا في دائرة
with support, with help,
مع دعم ,مع مساعدة
from people experienced in this kind of reconciliation.
من الناس من ذوي الخبرة في هذا النوع من المصالحة.
And Aicha started,
و بدأت عائشة
and she said,
و قالت
"I don't know if my son
"انا لا اعلم ما اذا كان ابني
is guilty or innocent,
مذنب ام بريء
but I want to tell you how sorry I am
لكن اريد ان اخبركم عن مدى اسفي
for what happened to your families.
لما حدث لعائلاتكم
I know what it is to suffer,
انا اعرف ما هي المعاناة
and I feel that if there is a crime,
و انا اشعر ان ,اذا كان هنالك جريمة
a person should be tried fairly and punished."
الشخص يجب ان يحاكم بعدل و يعاقب"
But she reached out to us in that way,
لكنها و صلت الينا بتلك الطريقة
and it was, I'd like to say, it was an ice-breaker.
و كان .اريد ان اقول انه كان كاسر للحاجز بيينا
And what happened then is we all told our stories,
و ما حدث هو اننا كلنا اخبرنا قصصنا
and we all connected as human beings.
و كلنا متصلين ككائنات بشرية
By the end of the afternoon --
بنهاية اليوم
it was about three hours after lunch --
كان حوالي ثلاث ساعات بعد الغداء
we'd felt as if we'd known each other forever.
شعرنا كما اننا نعرف بعضنا منذ الابد
Now what I learned from her,
الان ما تعلمته منها
is a woman, not only who could be so generous
ان امرأة ليس فقط بإمكانها ان تكون كريمة جدا
under these present circumstances
في ظل هذه الظروف
and what it was then,
و ما كان حينذاك
and what was being done to her son,
و ما كان يحدث لابنها
but the life she's had.
لكن الحياة التي عاشتها
I never had met
انا لم التقي
someone with such a hard life,
بشخص بهذه الحياة الصعبة
from such a totally different culture and environment from my own.
من بيئة و ثقافة مختلفة كليا من بيئتي
And I feel
و اشعر
that we have
اننا لدينا
a special connection,
اتصال خاص
which I value very much.
الذي اقدره جدا
And I think it's all about
و انا اعتقد انه كل شيء عن
being afraid of the other,
كوننا خائفين من بعضنا
but making that step
لكن عمل تلك الخطوة
and then realizing, "Hey, this wasn't so hard.
و ثم ادراك" لم يكن ذلك صعبا
Who else can I meet that I don't know,
من ايضا استطيع ان اقابل و لا اعرفه
or that I'm so different from?"
او انه انا مختلفة جدا الان؟"
So, Aicha,
اذن ,عائشة
do you have a couple of words
الديك بعض الكلمات
for conclusion?
للخاتمة؟
Because our time is up.
لان وقتنا انتهى
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Translator) AW: I wanted to say
(المترجم)عائشة: اردت ان اقول
that we have to try to know other people, the other.
اننا يجب ان نحاول معرفة اشخاص اخرين ,الاخر
You have to be generous,
يجب ان تكون كريما
and your hearts must be generous,
و قلبك يجب ان يكون كريما
your mind must be generous.
عقلك يجب ان يكون كريما
You must be tolerant.
يجب ان تكون متسامحا
You have to fight against violence.
يجب ان تحارب ضد العنف
And I hope that someday we'll all live together
و انا اتمنى يوما ما ان نعيش كلنا سويا
in peace and respecting each other.
في سلام و احترام بعضنا
This is what I wanted to say.
هذا ما اردت قوله
(Applause)
(تصفيق)